[SPEAKER_00]: Today's sutta is the Majjhima Nikāya Sālekha Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Majjhima Nikāya Eighth Sālekha Sutta, as we translated it, wearing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, thus have I heard.
[SPEAKER_00]: At one time, the auspicious one was staying near Savatthi in Jeta's Grove, Anathapindika's monastery.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the late afternoon, Venerable Mahācunda came out of retreat and went to the auspicious one.
[SPEAKER_00]: He bowed and sat to one side and said to the auspicious one,
[SPEAKER_00]: Said to the auspicious one, eh... venerable sir, there are many different views that arise in the world, connected with the assertions about the self or the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does the abandoning and relinquishing of those views come about in a bhikkhu who attends merely to the fundamentals of the training?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha repeats Chunda.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are many different views that arise in the world, connected with assertions about the self or the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Abhikūr relinquishes and abandons these views by seeing as it is with right understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where they arise, where they settle, and where they operate, as this is not mine, I'm not this, this is not myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, full understanding of the views is the way to relinquish them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the Buddha goes on and says, it is possible that a certain bhikkhu, having thoroughly withdrawn himself from sensuality, having withdrawn from unbeneficial phenomena, with thinking and with pondering, with joy and ease born of that withdrawal, might abide having entered upon the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He might think he's practicing wearing away, as in, like, wearing away of defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, in the training of the Noble Ones, these are not called wearing away, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: the first jhāna is not called wearing away, it's called easeful abiding in the present experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, he goes on to say, it is possible that Sambhikhu, with the appeasement of thinking and pondering, with internal confidence and collectedness of mind, without thinking and pondering... wait, what?
[SPEAKER_00]: It is possible that Sambhikhu, with the appeasement of thinking and pondering... aha!
[SPEAKER_00]: With the appeasement of thinking and pondering, with internal confidence and correctness of mind, without thinking and pondering, with joy and ease born of composure, might enter upon the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with appeasement of thinking and pondering, the thinking and pondering is without... he's without.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he can then experience joy and ease born of that composure and abide in the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He might think he's practicing wearing away, but in the training of the Noble Ones, these are not called wearing away, they're called easeful abidings with the present experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for the third jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same goes for the fourth jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to read it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he goes even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says that it is possible that Saṃbhīku, having fully surmounted perceptions of form, with the ending of perceptions of resistance, not attending to the perceptions of multiplicity, knows that space is infinite, might abide having entered upon the extent of that infinite space.
[SPEAKER_00]: He might think this is practicing wearing away,
[SPEAKER_00]: But in the training of the noble ones, these are not called wearing away, they are called peaceful abidings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Goes further into the fully surmounting the extent of infinite space, knowing that consciousness is infinite, abiding upon the extent of infinite consciousness, but that too is not wearing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, having fully surmounted the extent of infinite consciousness, knowing that there is nothing, might abide having entered upon the extent of that nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, that too is not wearing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a peaceful abiding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it is possible that Saṃbhiko, having fully surmounted the extent of nothingness, might abide entering upon the extent of neither perception nor non-perception.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he might think he's practicing wearing away, but in the training of the Noble Ones, these are not called wearing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're called peaceful abidings.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, the Buddha goes to explain what actually is
[SPEAKER_00]: Wearing away of the defilements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as it is here, Chandra, that wearing away should be practiced like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be cruel, but here we will not be cruel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will kill living creatures, but we will not kill living creatures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will steal, but we will not steal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will not be celibate,
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will not be celibate, but we will be celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will lie, we won't lie.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will speak divisively, speak harshly, engage in frivolous talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: We won't speak divisively, speak harshly, or engage in frivolous talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be covetous, with ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: We won't be covetous, and we will not have ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will have wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: We'll have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others have wrong intention, wrong speech, wrong action, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong recollectedness, wrong composure, wrong knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the wrong, the non-noble, hateful part.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will have wrong liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: We will have the right liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be overcome with indolence and lethargy.
[SPEAKER_00]: We will be rid of indolence and lethargy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be restless, we will not be restless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will have doubts, be irritable, be resentful, will denigrate, be contentious, be jealous, be stingy, be devious, deceitful, obstinate, arrogant.
[SPEAKER_00]: We won't be any of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be hard to admonish, but we will not be hard to admonish.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will have bad friends, we will have good friends.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be negligent, we will be diligent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be faithless, we will have faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be shameless, we will be ashamed of wrongdoing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be imprudent, we will be prudent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unlearned, we will be learned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lazy, we will be effortful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will have muddled recollectedness, we will have recollectedness properly established.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, before I go further, let's just go through this part.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, as you can see, like, jhānas are not the wearing away, and instead of these kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, almost like mundane things, you know, like everybody knows, okay, we shouldn't be cruel, we shouldn't lie still.
[SPEAKER_00]: How is that wearing away?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because surely enough, you know, if you look at the just, you know, the vast majority of Buddhist instructions today, the practice is, you know, the meditation, the jhāna and the meditative experiences.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not according to this sutta, obviously not according to the other suttas, but anyway, just if you look at this sutta, you realize that
[SPEAKER_00]: Having developed jhāna rightly, being withdrawn from sensuality, being withdrawn from hindrances, with thinking and pondering, pleasure and joy and borderless seclusion, that is the result of the right strivings, of the right efforts, of the right surmountings, of the right contemplations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why first jhāna, second jhāna, third jhāna, fourth jhāna... Not that, oh, they're irrelevant or they're pointless or secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, they're pretty much already types of a fruit of the right effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if a person is rightly contemplating the danger in sensuality, as that Anguttara Nikaya, early one, says, I can't remember the number, says basically that one can enter jhāna having not
[SPEAKER_00]: Understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger, gratification and the escape in regards to sensuality, that's not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could see that's the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the wearing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Diligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Diligent contemplation of the hindrances, unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not abstractly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where this second part, the exposition of wearing away, kind of hammers it in.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like theoretical spreading of loving kindness and wishing well everybody and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like
[SPEAKER_00]: Literal daily choices that you make by body, speech and mind that pertain to cruelty, killing, stealing, not being celibate, lying, speaking divisively, harshly, frivolously, harboring covetousness, ill-will mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are choices that you are accepting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind, as I say often, can come up with these things and you can't prevent that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can certainly prevent adding more fuel to that fire through your own non-diligent, ignorant, wrongly emphasized choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be cruel.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the whole world can be cruel.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole world can find justifications for killing, stealing, lying, speaking divisively.
[SPEAKER_00]: I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter the reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I won't choose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will be presented with an option.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could be cruel, I could be harsh, I could be rude, I could be disrespectful, I could be killing, stealing, I could not be celibate, but I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the training, as we often say, as the suttas repeat left and right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exercising the right choices towards skillful by body, speech, and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just adopting them, because the authority told you so, but because you are actually wanting to train your citta through those choices, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: those actions, or abstaining from certain actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like... same like that other sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it may be in Majjhima as well, where it was those different arahants, when they listed
[SPEAKER_00]: When they were asked, like, what's the most amazing thing, what's the single thing that everybody should develop, and then they kind of listed their abilities, they were kind of... that they developed in the process of arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha came, and then they asked him, and he says, yeah, whatever, all of you, which is, you know, he was a jhāna master, he was this, he was that, he was the Prabhupāda Mahārāja, he says, yeah, yeah, all that's great, but actually, the most correct answer, that one factor, that is the most important, was none of those special powers and results and liberations, it was the diligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it was the diligence as a factor that made them individually develop all those amazing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is kind of the same, like you think, like, oh, first jhāna, second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, that's the correct result of correct practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by all means, it should be strived for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you should, by all means, make the effort to withdraw your mind from hindrances and sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: To remove the weight of sensual desire from your citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could see, like, if somebody develops that and then abides in a state that, basically, citta is not touched by debt, prison, danger, all those similes that the first jhāna described, one can think, like, oh, wow, this is that purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is that... this is what's bringing me to arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, well, actually, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was the work that you did beforehand that led you to that point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, in that another sutta, he actually says, like, it was a sutta that says that, basically, arahantship can be attained on the basis of first jhāna, second jhāna, third jhāna, fourth jhāna, which is kind of used to
[SPEAKER_00]: to show that, yes, you need to have at least the first jhāna to the extent necessary for the other hundred.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then the Buddha described it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, like, you will have a monk or something who would be... who develops the first jhāna and abides in it, and then I would tell him
[SPEAKER_00]: After that, that, okay, now, regard everything in that first jhāna, everything that's skillful, noble, cleansed, debt-free, regard that as peril, that, that, as everything else you regard, basically, as all the ways you regard essentiality that led you towards the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, continue regarding the first jhāna in that way as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: So that his mind completely turns away from that noble state, so to speak, because then it will be impossible to return anything lower than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's that kind of exercising the right choice, recognizing the the choice that's influenced by
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust, aversion, distraction, obviously, all these, how many, 44 or something, all these other negative factors, but obviously, they all boil down to exercising the choice that's still, like, either rooted in ignorance, rooted in complacency, rooted in lack of diligence, rooted in lack of contemplation, or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't have to... and why this sutta is so good, it's because you don't have to wait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I've got to wait for the first jhāna, to practice those first jhāna, then I'll start exercising all of these right practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: These right practices is what's leading you in the direction of jhāna anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, on a day-to-day basis, whenever you are presented with the choice to follow wrong intention, or to abstain from it, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you're presented to engage in frivolous talk, to relish it, to enjoy it, do you follow it or do you say, no, I'll abstain from it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever the mind wants to speak behind someone's back, derive satisfaction from speaking divisively or gossiping, do you accept it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you accept that offer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you accept that possibility?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you say no?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you don't forget what should be recollected and where the emphasis should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the training.
[SPEAKER_00]: Body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, it can't be any clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sutta cannot summarize it in any clearer manner than this, as to what is the training that leads to the complete purification of the mind and liberation and jhāna and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly why, like, see, it goes, after the Buddha goes to all this describing of what actually is wearing away, the next section is the exposition of, by intent, eye choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of these are choices that people make.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I keep saying, that's the difference between having your mind say, come up with the choice, options for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I could be non-celibate on this occasion.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could say a lie on this occasion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not your problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your choice is, do you accept the given options?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: These choices lead the way for purification.
[SPEAKER_00]: These choices don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where the next... the next section says, Chunda, I say that even the arising of intent towards beneficial qualities is very helpful, let alone following that embodied speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consequently, then, the opposite has to be true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the arising of the intent towards unbeneficial qualities is not very helpful, let alone following those thoughts in body and speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you should give rise to following intents, following choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I intend to choose rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: When presented with cruelty, killing, stealing, all the precepts, non-celibacy, negligence, faithlessness, shamelessness, imprudence, being unlearned, I will choose the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will maintain the intent to choose the right thing, to abstain from the pull
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the grain, with the current of all these unskillful choices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, Willie gives the example.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... Chunda, suppose there was an uneven path and another even path to circumvent it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, suppose there's an uneven ford and another even ford to circumvent it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, a cruel individual circumvents the cruelty by not being cruel.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no third option.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, let me... let me do a bit of both and find my way out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these are the binary choices when it comes to... That's why they boil down to this core of the... of the intent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cruelty, ill-will, sensual desire, hindrances, because there is no middle ground there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're either allowing the animal to control you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Accepting the given options, pressures, stuff that's been speaking into your ear, or not, and maintaining perspective in face of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not very complex, but, yeah, that doesn't mean it's easy.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, an individual who is attached to his own views, holding them tight, refusing to let them go, circumvents it by not being attached to his own views, not holding tight, by letting them go easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you let go of the views?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by questioning them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you blindly defending the standpoints and views because they provide you with a sense of safety, confidence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you willing, at any given moment, to question your views?
[SPEAKER_00]: If a question presents itself, you won't shy away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will follow it through, even if it proves that you were completely wrong in the core of your being, for what you believed in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you overcome your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, Chunda, all unbeneficial qualities lead downwards, while all beneficial qualities lead upwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same way, a cruel individual goes upwards by not being cruel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by exercising the right choices, the mind's going upwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he goes to the... the last bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're sinking in the mud yourself, Chunda, it is quite impossible for you to pull out someone else who is also sinking in the mud.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're not sinking in the mud yourself, it is quite possible for you to pull out someone else who is sinking in the mud.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are not tamed, trained, quenched yourself, it is quite impossible for you to help tame, train and quench someone else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you are tamed, trained and quenched yourself, it is quite possible for you to tame
[SPEAKER_00]: Train and quench somebody else.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, kind of common sense, you would think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the same way, a cruel individual quenches by not being cruel.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one quenches the mind, trains the mind, develops the right view, has the mind going upwards,
[SPEAKER_00]: By exercising... by maintaining the right intent, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: the right context, and by exercising the right choices on the basis of that intent, which, see, intent is already a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose to ignore the context or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like a more general choice, on account of which you will be then exercising more specific choices that are right, that are going... circumventing the bad ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it says, so, Chunda, I've told the expositions of wearing away, arousing intent, the way around, going up and quenching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of compassion, I've done what teachers should do, who wants... what a teacher should do, who wants what is best for his disciples.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here are the roots of trees, here the empty huts, develop jhāna, Chunda, do not be negligent, do not regret it later, this is my instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, by the way, this part developed jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like jhāna is just used as a verb, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just means contemplate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplate, chunda, don't be negligent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean enter the first jhāna or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you practice contemplation rightly, correctly, surmount the unwholesome things, withdraw them, withdraw your mind from them sufficiently, you will enter the first comprehension, as I like to call it.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of the wearing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of the right practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, you know what to do, rest.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then it says, this is what the auspicious one said, pleased, venerable Mahārāja Chunda delighted in what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says, 44 items have been stated, organized into five sections.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wearing away is the name of this discourse, which is deep as the ocean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of the core, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just ties into, like, even... because, you know, you had, like, you had those...
[SPEAKER_00]: Complex... well... say, more kind of advanced, higher types of instructions, detailed expositions on patitsaṁpāda, this or that, which, you know, would go over people's heads, generally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you had those instructions given to some monks and nuns.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go to seclusion and anything that you know is unbeneficial, don't cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything you know is beneficial, cultivate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They did that for three months, came back, arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, those kind of polar opposites on two different, like, ends of, well, same spectrum of right instruction, but very two different, like, very far apart, resulted in arahantship.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the detailed advanced expositions resulted in arahantship for some, and then just abandoned the unbeneficial qualities.
[SPEAKER_00]: That resulted in arahantship for another.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this kind of sutta shows you how.
[SPEAKER_00]: It shows you what's in common to both, which is basically that core principle of exercising the skillful choice at the expense of the unskillful one by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to be aware of the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I keep saying, like, yes, you can take on the precepts because the authority told you so and it can help you in the beginning, but if it's kept at the arm's length,
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's kept as a duty that I must blindly adhere to and never allow my mind to, you know, think about and maybe highlight that there is always a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, at any given point you can get up and not be a monk anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does that choice scare you, thinking about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does the mind get wild when that's... when that option is presented?
[SPEAKER_00]: Means you are not training anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just keeping it down, covered up.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's not just enough to memorize these 44 items and then just automatically always choose right.
[SPEAKER_00]: The choice needs to be felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Needs to be...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something you need to be conscious of.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I could actually...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's 50-50.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could get up and leave, but I choose not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could say something unwholesome, but I choose not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the missing kind of aspect, angle, in people's practice, in people who keep the precepts and do everything rightly, but still don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means they're doing it through Sīlabhātparamāsa.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're doing it at the arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're doing it kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, through at least a degree of avoiding of responsibility for that core choice, you could stop doing it at any given moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, you can use the environment, use tradition, use the learning, use all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, I'll take on the precepts in that sense, but not to shy away or mask the choice that you have every day to maintain it or abandon it, to practice or not, but to actually be able to come closer to it
[SPEAKER_00]: Without your mind overwhelming you in a kind of excitement towards the prospect of letting it loose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's that level, the right level of endurance and the right level of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, obviously, you have to be patient about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just decide the right level where you're gonna decide the right things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It needs to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I said what do all these things converge upon, they converge upon the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's in common to all those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the fact that it's your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others may do it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: We won't do it here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, almost like we, as in like me and my own mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, look, two of us, we're not doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be non-celibate.
[SPEAKER_00]: We won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Others will be negligent.
[SPEAKER_00]: We won't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm choosing for both of us, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ajahn, does this mean that the Buddha answered Venerable Chöndor's question if the fundamentals are enough?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, but you need to drill them in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or no, there is more to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I, not just purification of the body and speech, but by mind as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like
[SPEAKER_00]: The views are not gonna automatically fall off just if somebody's, as I say, virtuous, keeping the precepts and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, the effort needs to be made with, like, right contemplation, diligence, in regard to hindrances, in regard to all the, you know, unwholesome choices that carry the roots of
[SPEAKER_00]: Greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, like, well, there is more to it, yes, but not like more to it you do something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, there is more of the same thing, but it needs to be done, like, on the mental level, well, without any tolerance for exceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's gradual.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you will not just magically be able to, like, keep your mind above sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, so you start physically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, keep your body out of the sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start verbally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Add verbal aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, don't talk about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't be, like, spreading gossip.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't be engaging in all these other compensating practices.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, comes to a point, it's like, oh, yeah, I can see that mental choice now, because I haven't been, obviously, muddying the water through, like, coarse physical or verbal actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the choice of those thoughts enduring in your mind is presented, and it's like, oh, I don't have to pick them up, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, I don't have to pick things up with my hand, when they're in front of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to destroy them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just need to not pick it up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I see the same principle mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thoughts have arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to pick them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't have to do anything about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just don't have to pick them up and I'm free from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order for that mental choice to become apparent, yeah, the the right physical and verbal choices need to be cultivated, well, sufficiently long.
[SPEAKER_00]: How long that is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, person will see.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's not like a preset time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ajahn, this might be related to the last question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Does the first part of the sutta suggest that people can get to the eighth jhāna without right view?
[SPEAKER_00]: You mean like the four immaterial attainment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes, other suttas do say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: A person can withdraw their mind rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And develop 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th jhāna and then the subsequent immaterial establishments of the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, again, even those people without the right view would be walking along the right lines.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they might not technically have had enough right instruction to see through their conceit and the sense of I am in that subtle way, but the only way to enter the first jhāna or go further is through abandoning sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like anāgāmī, like... but withdrawing your mind, completely drying it from sensuality internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Overcoming the five hindrances, again, not like an arahant permanently, but at least to the extent that you've been diligently practicing the way out of those things through understanding them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through, like, self-hypnotizing or something, where you are unaware of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, how can you... how can you be exercising right choices, as this sutta describes and says this is what wearing away actually is, that even jhāna is the result of,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are hypnotized, if you are unaware of the options, if you are completely oblivious to the context, to the intent, to what to choose, what's presented there, what mind leans towards... That's why any, that's what I keep saying, like any types of self-hypnosis or practice is just taking you away from where the actual work is done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, even the ones that have entered in the first jhāna,
[SPEAKER_00]: According to all the suttas, with thinking and pondering, enjoy born of withdrawal from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the knowledge that you are safe from the threat, safe from death, safe from prison, safe from danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to know that you are safe from the danger,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the only way to know... the only way to be safe from the danger and feel that safety is to fully understand the extent of danger, not to pretend that it's not there because you focused on your kneecaps or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, people can technically get jhānas without the right view, but, again, today the only actual
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowledge of jhānas, yes, okay, like putting aside the contemporary later interpretations and stuff like that, but sooner or later, people would basically fall back onto the suttas, because that's where the idea of jhāna comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that somebody can actually practice the jhānas rightly, for the jhānas rightly, and attain the jhānas rightly, without having understood the importance, the emphasis, the training aspect of citta, through these right choices, that's not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Technically, it's possible that somebody was doing it back in the day, because there were lots of not-as-wrong instructions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But today, that somebody can arrive at that, without having come across the right instruction of the Buddha and the suttas, it's highly unlikely, let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody were to develop the first jhāna or higher, it has to be developed through the exercising of the same right choices, same withdrawal from the same unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: They'll almost certainly get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even before their jhāna, pretty much.
[SPEAKER_00]: The next question... Ajahn, there is an intellectual understanding of the principles.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, sometimes, due to undeveloped mindfulness, the choices seem to have been made for you on some sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: What can we do to develop the right... How can the choices be made for you?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Choice cannot be made for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can certainly have very weighty options.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some options will be pressing you and threatening you more than others.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no choice can be made for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it's not a choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what people are afraid of, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you start approaching everything through the recognition of your choices, it can get very scary very quickly, because you realize, well, nothing obliges you to live or die.
[SPEAKER_00]: No external criteria, no external reason, no external... You choose them to... you choose those things as reasons, but you could then also choose them to stop being reasons, basically, for whatever you're doing or not doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, in existential philosophy, Sartre was referring to it, I remember, as a... once a person takes on the kind of existential responsibility, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: start taking responsibility for the choices and recognize that there is never... that it's actually impossible for choice to be made for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the one accepting it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: He called it as monstrous freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, when you recognize how free you actually are, it can be overwhelmingly frightful, scary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, at any given moment, anybody can just get up and walk out from anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that's scary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's something you have to get used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Getting closer to the recognition that choice always rests with you, mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter the options, no matter the weight of those options, no matter the repercussions, no matter the consequences, choice cannot be made for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, again, something I remember, like, it gets casually chanted, like, in the monasteries and stuff, like, oh, we are the owners of our karma, and it's like,
[SPEAKER_00]: People don't realize the extent of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think like, oh, yeah, we are the owners of...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, karma is choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Every action is intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no action without the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, choice, it's already something that pretty much sets and determines your karma, just as the sutra says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, just the rising of beneficial or unbeneficial intent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already.
[SPEAKER_00]: Taking you up or taking you down, let alone following through with body and speech and actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the common casual chant, well, we are the owners of our actions, like, yeah, through and through, all the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your action to choose to... your choice to choose to get up and continue living your life the way you live your life, that's your karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your choice to change, to do something about it, well, that's your karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, do you recognize how far that goes?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing that can come in between you and that freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the sooner you recognize that, the sooner you admit it, more importantly, well, the sooner can citta stop being afraid from it, of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will get used to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can be overwhelming in the beginning, but that's why you have the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're preventing you from spiraling into the unwanted directions, on account of the same freedom of choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the mind can settle in that, can get used to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it won't be as frightening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not a surprise anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the training becomes elevated.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, now you can... you can get closer to that edge of freedom and really purify it, really develop the right intent, maintain that right intent, right context, and then all the... all the presented options to choose these 44 unwholesome things or 44 opposites.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will know what to choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will know what to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will know what not to, like, tolerate, to give in and add more fuel to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's the same instruction, same principle they would have started from the beginning, like in the, say, early stages of training.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is already now the higher refinement of your citta.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, as I said, in some of the suttas, that's all people needed to become arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the same principle goes all the way through.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, regarding this last question, you could see that due to the undeveloped mindfulness, the choices seem to have been made for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you chose lack of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why subsequent choices felt automatic.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you didn't choose the lack of mindfulness, abandonment of the context, willingly, those choices would have remained seen, not just submitted to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, nothing, nothing can come between you and your responsibility for everything you choose, big or small.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ajahn, I think you mentioned before that one usually tries to get rid of one hindrance through another hindrance, and that's how one ends up accepting some hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you speak more about this?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't quite remember what was the context of that, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I just meant, basically, a person is just acting out of hindrances, because they're trying to get rid of the entire options presented.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's put it that way in the context of today's talk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the problem with hindrances... For example, maybe there's a version, you have a version to another version, and try to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can have aversion to your aversion, but... you might not be able to help that, but it's like, do you go about it the right way or the wrong way?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you trying to get rid of the choices of aversion, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: your citta, that's affected with aversion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, are you recognizing that that's the original state of things?
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Sutta says, he knows the mind of anger as mind of anger, mind of lust as mind of lust, not he tries to change it, and wrestle it, and tackle it, and get rid of it, and tailor it to his liking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowledge is the way you tailor it to your liking, knowing it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have a mind of aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know that the choices to speak, to say something, to do something on account of this aversion, are bound.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those options are your state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not trying to get rid of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead, you are choosing to not accept the aversion while it's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the subtle difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: And why is that difference important?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where your choice is.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, it would be easier if I could just remove the tempting things, including my mind states, so I don't have to feel the edge of the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's why people fail to free themselves from hindrances and just end up from one falling into the other or going in circles, basically, and then
[SPEAKER_00]: Developing a view that pretty much self-induced oblivion of hypnosis and half-asleep state of concentrations is the only possible peace they can know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because either mind bothers you or you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no third option.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, again, others will be cruel, others will be non-self, others will follow sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of these are listed things in this sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are options that citta will come up with, through interaction with the senses and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, but I will choose not to.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not add fuel.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not add further choices of this that would then kind of start adding towards the actions by body and speech and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how long the possibility for cruelty remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter how long the possibility for non-celibacy remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: For negligence remains.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to you is to no exceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't accept it and you don't fuel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I say one tries to get rid of the hindrance, means one tries to get rid of the entire experience as a whole, the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: I read all the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Buddha said it's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must make this whole thing go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, usually, those... those... those suttas where the Buddha talks about, like this... somebody who already sees their citta, somebody who's already saw the pañña, you know, like that... the five ways of stilling your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the Abhi citta training.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's somebody who's already been exercising the right choices and used things on right level, recognizes citta, the animal, for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he can refine it in those other five ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, without seeing your citta, those five ways just become five excuses to try to get rid of the things, because they bother you and you're already averse towards the whole experience.